

Roberto Verdecchia

PH D. CANDIDATE IN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING

■ roberto.verdecchia@gssi.it | robertoverdecchia.github.io | robertoverdecchia

Summary.

Double Ph.D. Candidate of the Computer Science Department at the Gran Sasso Science Institute (GSSI) and of the Software and Services group at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam (VU). Member of the Netherlands Research School for Information and Kwnoledge Systems (SIKS). Fascinated by empirical software engineering, especially when applied in the fields of software architecture, technical debt, software testing, and software energy efficiency.

Education

Gran Sasso Science Institute(GSSI) & Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam (VU)

Double Ph.D. Candidate in Software Engineering

• Tentative dissertation title: "Identification and Management of Architectural Technical Debt"

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam (VU)

M.Sc. in Computer Science: Software Engineering curriculum

• Thesis title: "Static and Dynamic Analysis of Software Energy Efficiency in Industry" (Cum Laude distinction)

University of Florence - School of Engineering (UniFi)

B.Eng. in Computer Engineering

• Thesis title: "Algorithm for Weather-based Naval Routing as an N-stage Decisional Process"

L'Aquila, Italy Amsterdam, The

Netherlands

Nov. 2016 - Present

Amsterdam, The Netherlands

2014 - 2016

2011 - 2014

Florence, Italy

Work Experience _____

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Amsterdam, The Netherlands

2015 - Present

- · Courses: Software Testing, Software Architecture, Service Oriented Design, Software Modeling, Service Science
- Responsibilities: Supervise B.Sc/M.Sc Theses, and research projects. Conduct lectures, seminars and exercise sessions. Tutor teams of students. Review exams and deliverables. Manage e-learning platforms. Attend weekly meetings with instructors to align course content.

KPMGAmsterdam, The Netherlands

GRADUATE RESEARCH INTERN

Apr. 2016 - Oct. 2016

- Graduate research intern focusing on the analysis of software products
- Responsibilities: Architecture reconstruction. Static and dynamic analysis of code bases. Server management. Performance testing. Automation scripting. Statistical data analysis

OMALA Amsterdam, The Netherlands

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN

Jun. 2015 - Aug. 2015

- Software engineering intern focusing on the analysis of a large scale heterogeneous system of systems
- Responsibilities: Requirements engineering and architecture trade-off analysis for the Airport Garden City IT infrastructure project of the Lelystad Airport business park

Honors & Awards

ACM-SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award, IEEE-ACM International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE) 2019 Montreal, Canada Paper: Scalable Approaches for Test Suite Reduction Best Paper Award, Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS) 2019 Hawaii, U.S.A Paper: DecidArch: Playing Cards as Software Architects ISSIP-IBM-CBA Student Paper Award for Best Industry Studies Paper, Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS) 2019 Hawaii, U.S.A Paper: DecidArch: Playing Cards as Software Architects 2018 Best Early Career Researcher Award, IEEE International Conference on Software Architecture (ICSA) Seattle, U.S.A Runner-up Best Paper Award, International Conference on ICT for Sustainability (ICT4S) 2018 Toronto, Canada Paper: Empirical Evaluation of the Energy Impact of Refactoring Code Smells Bronze medal - ACM Student Research Competition, IEEE/ACM International Conference on Mobile Gothenburg, Software Engineering and System (MobileSoft 2018) 2018 Sweden

Paper: Identifying Architectural Technical Debt in Android Applications through Compliance Checking

Visiting

SEDC Lab, ISTI-CNR (Italian National Research Council)

Pisa, Italy

VISITING RESEARCH SCHOLAR July 2019

• Topic: Fast static approaches for test flakiness prediction

· Host: Antonia Bertolino

VISITING RESEARCH SCHOLAR

Electrical and Computer Engineering Department (University of British Columbia)

Vancouver, Canada

April 2019 - June 2019

• Topic: Grounded theory on architectural technical debt

Host: Philippe Kruchten

SEDC Lab, ISTI-CNR (Italian National Research Council)

Pisa, Italy

VISITING RESEARCH SCHOLAR July 2018

• Topic: Scalable Approaches for Test Suite Reduction

• Host: Antonia Bertolino

SEDC Lab, ISTI-CNR (Italian National Research Council)

Pisa, Italy

VISITING RESEARCH SCHOLAR July 2017

• Topic: FAST Approaches to Scalable Similarity-based Test Case Prioritization

• Host: Antonia Bertolino

Services

Program Committee member SOFTENG (2020), GREEN (2019)

External Journal Reviewer IST (2019)

ICSE (2018, 2019), ICSA (2018, 2019), ECSA (2018, 2019), MOBILESoft (2018, 2019), **External Conference Reviewer**

ESEC/FSE (2018), ICT4S (2018, 2019)

Student Volunteer ICSE (2018, 2019), ICPE (2018)

Publications.

• R. Verdecchia, I. Malavolta, and P. Lago. Guidelines for Architecting Android Apps: A mixed-method Empirical Study. International Conference on Software Architecture (ICSA), 2019.

• E. Cruciani, B. Miranda, R. Verdecchia, A. Bertolino. Scalable Approaches for Test Suite Reduction. International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), 2019. **T** ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award.

• P. Lago, Jia F. Cai, Remco C. de Boer, Philippe Kruchten, and R. Verdecchia. DecidArch v2: An improved Game to teach Architecture Design Decision Making. International Workshop on decision Making in Software ARCHitecture (MARCH), 2019.

• P. Lago, Jia F. Cai, Remco C. de Boer, Philippe Kruchten, and R. Verdecchia. DecidArch: Playing Cards as Software Architects. Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS), 2019. * Best Paper Award. * ISSIP-IBM-CBA Student Paper Award for Best Industry Studies Paper.

• R. Verdecchia, I. Malavolta, and P. Lago. Architectural Technical Debt Identification: The Research Landscape. International Conference on Technical Debt (TechDebt), 2018.

• I. Malavolta, R. Verdecchia, M. Bruntink, B. Filipovic and P. Lago. On the Evolution of Maintainability Issues of Android Applications IEEE International Conference on Software Maintenance and Evolution (ICSME), 2018.

• R. Verdecchia, R. A. Saez, Giuseppe Procaccianti, and P. Lago. Empirical Evaluation of the Energy Impact of Refactoring Code Smells. International Conference on ICT for Sustainability (ICT4S), 2018. TRunner-up Best Paper Award.

• R. Verdecchia, A. Guldner, Y. Becker, and E. Kern. Code-level Energy Hotspot Localization via Naive Spectrum Based Testing. International Conference On Environmental Informatics (Envirolnfo), 2018.

• R. Verdecchia. Identifying Architectural Technical Debt: Moving Forward. IEEE International Conference On Software Architectura (ICSA), 2018.

• B. Miranda, E. Cruciani, R. Verdecchia, A. Bertolino. FAST Approaches to Scalable Similarity-based Test Case Prioritization. International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), 2018.

• R. Verdecchia. Identifying Architectural Technical Debt in Android Applications through Compliance Checking. International Conference on Mobile Software Engineering and Systems (MobileSoft), 2018. 🜪 Bronze medal - ACM Student Research Competition.

• R. Verdecchia, Giuseppe Procaccianti, I. Malavolta, P. Lago, and J. Koedijk. Estimating Energy Impact of Software Releases and Deployment Strategies: The KPMG Case Study. Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement (ESEM), 2017.

• R. Verdecchia, F. Ricchiuti, A. Hankel, P. Lago, and Giuseppe Procaccianti. Green ICT Research and Challenges. Advances and New Trends in Environmental Informatics, pp. 37-48, 2017.

Skills

Programming **Databases**

Python, R, Bash, C++, Java, GO, Scala MySQL, MongoDB, Cassandra Selenium, JMeter, Android, Kafka,

Spark, Docker, GCP, Jenkins

Typesetting LaTeX **Version Control** Git, SVN

> Italian (native), German (native), English, Dutch, Spanish Languages

Frameworks/tools